A Guide to the Papers of the President of the University of Virginia, Office Administrative Files, 1925-1930
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the President of the University of Virginia, Office Administrative Files 1925-1930
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-2/1/2.472 VII
This collection consists of ca. 2900 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access restrictions may apply to specific student records under the terms of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (F.E.R.P.A.).
Scope and Content Information
These files (ca. 2,900 items) constitute the major record series generated by Edwin Anderson Alderman, the first president of the University of Virginia. The records consist chiefly of correspondence, but also include reports, minutes, clippings, memoranda, and related papers concerning all areas of business of the president's office.
Process Information
Archival transfer, Office of the President, 1980 April 22. Originally accessioned as MSS 2636-b, 1947 November 15. Blueprint transferred to RG-31/2/11.811.
Contents List
- "A" Miscellaneous --Abbot, Lawrence, editor of Outlook--re Vergil celebration, Thomas Jefferson; Abernethy, Charles L., Congressman from North Carolina; Academy of Political Science; Adams, Samuel L., delegate in General Assembly, expressing opposition to anti-prohibition speakers and professors; American Council on Education; American Philosophical Society; Amphitheater--amplifier equipment; Angell, James, president of Yale 1925-1930, (4 folders) (Box 1)
- Academic Schools, Miscellaneous--Journalism 1925-1930 (Box 1)
- Administrative Council 1925-1930 (Box 1)
- Advertising 1925-1930 (Box 1)
- Agriculture--report on agricultural education 1925-1930 (Box 1)
- Alumni Board Allotments from Contingent Fund guaranteed by Alumni Board of Trustees 1925-1930 (Box 1)
- Alumni Board General Correspondence--Reports on Endowment Fund 1925-1930 (Box 1)
- Alumni Board Investments 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 1)
- Alumni Board Meetings--Report on Endowment Fund 1925-1930 (Box 2)
- Alumni Board Treasurer 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 2)
- Alumni Groups--General 1925-1930 (Box 2)
- Alumni Office 1925-1930 (Box 2)
- Annual Reports 1925-1930 (Box 2)
- Applications for Positions 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 2)
- Architect's File 1925-1930 (Box 2)
- Art, Architecture, Music--Carnegie Corporation scholarships in Fine Arts--Otto Kahn address; Kearny gift of pictures; proposed addition to Law School; Beaux Arts Ball; play-writing; gifts of art work 1925-1930 (Box 3)
- Articles about the University 1925-1930 (Box 3)
- Association of American Universities 1925-1930 (Box 3)
- Astronomy--Leander McCormick portrait; correspondence with Charles P. Olivier, professor 1925-1930 (Box 3)
- Athletics 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 3)
- "B" Miscellaneous (1-6 of 8)--Bagby, B.B., Chief Medical Inspector; Bureau of Health; Barr, Stringfellow; Battle, George Gordon; Bibliography; Boothe, Armistead L. 1925-1930 (Box 3)
- "B" Miscellaneous (7-8 of 8)--Brookings Institution; Bryan, John Stewart of the Richmond News Leader; Buchanan, Benjamin F.; Buenos Aires; Byrd, Harry F.; Byrd, Richard E. 1925-1930 (Box 4)
- Barbour-Page Lectures 1925-1930 (Box 4)
- Biblical History and Literature 1925-1930 (Box 4)
- Biology--Complaint from Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals re alleged snake fight; Andrew Fleming Prize in Biology 1925-1930 (Box 4)
- Blandy Farm bequest 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 4)
- Buildings and Grounds 1925-1930 (Box 4)
- Bursar, Business Manager 1925-1930 (Box 4)
- Bursar's Office 1925-1930 (Box 4)
- "C" Miscellaneous (1 of 8)--Calendar; Canby, Henry S., editor of the Saturday Review; Cannon, Bishop James, re prohibition; Carnegie Endowment for International Peace; Catalogue 1925-1930 (Box 4)
- "C" Miscellaneous (2-8 of 8)--Cemetery; Centennial medal, Century Association; Chamber of Commerce, Chandler, J.A.C., president, William and Mary; Chase, H. W., president, University of North Carolina; Citizens Committee of One Thousand; Cockrell, Ewing, re law enforcement; Colonnade Club; Columbia University; Administrative Committees of the faculty; Commonwealth Fund; Constitution; Coeducation; Cooperative Education Association of Virginia; Crenshaw, Lewis 1925-1930 (Box 5)
- Calendars, Weekly 1925-1930 (Box 5)
- Carnegie Foundation 1925-1930 (Box 5)
- Chemistry--American Chemical Society Prize Essay Contest; DuPont fellowships; research of John Yoe; teaching fellowships in the laboratory sciences 1925-1930 (Box 5)
- Commerce and Business Administration 1925-1930 (Box 5)
- Commons--cafeteria for students 1925-1930 (Box 5)
- Convocations--list of recipients of intermediate honors 1925-1930 (Box 5)
- Co-ordinate College --see also Fredericksburg College 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 6)
- Crime Commission--Davis, John W. 1925-1930 (Box 6)
- "D" Miscellaneous --Dabney, R. H.; Davis, Arthur Kyle; Davis, John Staige; Denny, George H., president, University of Alabama; Drewry, Patrick Henry, U. S. House of Representatives; drinking; Duke, Samuel, president, State Teachers College [James Madison], Harrisonburg, Virginia; DuPont, Alfred 1925-1930, (3 folders) (Box 6)
- Dean's Office, J. M. Page--regulations; freshman failure in Virginia colleges 1925-1930 (Box 6)
- Delta Tau Delta 1925-1930 (Box 6)
- Dormitories (1-2 of 3) 1925-1930 (Box 6)
- Dormitories (3 of 3) 1925-1930 (Box 7)
- DuPont Bequest 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 7)
- "E" Miscellaneous --Edmunds, Mrs. J.E. re paintings; Elliott, Milton C.; English Speaking Union 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 7)
- Economics--proposal to create a Bureau of Business research in the Commerce School 1925-1930 (Box 7)
- Education --student teaching 1925-1930, (2 folders ) (Box 7)
- Education, Nursing 1925-1930 (Box 7)
- Engineering Department, General--Industrial survey of Waynesboro 1925-1930 (Box 7)
- English 1925-1930 (Box 7)
- Evolution 1925-1930 (Box 7)
- University Extension--Extension Topics (1 of 2) 1925-1930 (Box 7)
- University Extension (2 of 2) 1925-1930 (Box 8)
- "F" Miscellaneous --Faculty; Fees; Fess, Simeon D., U. S. Senator, re drinking; Fitz-Hugh, Thomas; Flexner, Abraham; Foreign Policy Association; Fox Movietone News re shots taken at the University; Fraternities; Freeman, Douglas Southall 1925-1930, (3 folders) (Box 8)
- Faculty Apartments 1925-1930 (Box 8)
- Fellowships and Scholarships 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 8)
- Filing Material 1925-1930 (Box 8)
- Finals 1925-1930 (Box 8)
- Finances--Budget; Phi Kappa Psi land value 1925-1930 (Box 9)
- Forestry--Proposal to move location of State Forester's office from the University; Seward Forest bequest 1925-1930 (Box 9)
- Forms 1925-1930 (Box 9)
- Foundations, Boards, etc. 1925-1930 (Box 9)
- Founder's Day--Nicholas Murray Butler 1925-1930 (Box 9)
- Fredericksburg College--recommendations for new presidency; see also Co-ordinate College 1925-1930 (Box 9)
- Funds, Loan 1925-1930 (Box 9)
- "G" Miscellaneous --Gault, Robert H.; Gee, Wilson; Guggenheim Foundation 1925-1930, (3 folders) (Box 10)
- General Education Board 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 10)
- Geological Survey 1925-1930 (Box 10)
- Geology 1925-1930 (Box 10)
- Gift 1925-1930 (Box 10)
- Governor's Office--Byrd visit; Budget report to Byrd after reorganization of state government; keynote speech, Byrd, Harrisonburg; Trinkle, Stone Mountain Memorial "Harvest Campaign" coins; salary for Watson; insurance letter re dynamite in Cabell Hall; R. E. Byrd North Pole conquest; gifts to University of Virginia.; DuPont Trust; alcohol at UVa. 1925-1930 (Box 11)
- Graduate Dept.--statistics; expansion; fellowship 1925-1930 (Box 11)
- Greek 1925-1930 (Box 11)
- "H" Miscellaneous --Hartridge, Evelyn B. re Julien Green; Hollins College; Hoover, Herbert 1925-1930, (6 folders) (Box 11)
- Higher Education 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 11)
- Higher Education, Education Survey Report and Commission to Unify Higher Education 1925-1930 (Box 11)
- History --complaints over lack of office space and lecture rooms 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 12)
- History Department Research Professorship in Southern History 1925-1930 (Box 12)
- Honor System 1925-1930 (Box 12)
- "I" Miscellaneous--Institute of Citizenship and Government; Institute of International Education; Institute for Research in the Social Sciences; Institute of Public Affairs 1925-1930 (Box 12)
- Invitations to be represented 1925-1930, (4 folders) (Box 12)
- Institute for Research in the Social Sciences (1of 5)--gifted children; Wilson Gee; Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial; Committee recommendations for formation of Institute: Gee, Gooch, Ferguson, Smithey, Malone, Kincaid; Second Conference on Teaching and Research in the Social Sciences, Southern Region, at UVa., March 1926; D. W. Willard; Howard W. Odum; candidates for professor of sociology 1925-1926 (Box 12a)
- Institute for Research in the Social Sciences (2 of 5)--all correspondence with Rockefeller Memorial, including lengthy letters from Alderman, and a memorandum for Alderman on a conference with Professor Odum at Chapel Hill, NC re the Rockefeller Grant 1926 Jan- Jun (Box 12a)
- Institute for Research in the Social Sciences (3 of 5)--Applications and recommendations for head of Institute; H.W. Chase, President, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill; Gee re responsibility of University of Virginia to public welfare in Virginia; alumni of Richmond to set up research professorship in Social Sciences; minutes of meeting, Alderman, Smithey, Snavely, and Gee, setting up Research Council; State Board of Public Welfare plan for School of Social Sciences at University of Virginia; Frank Bane; Dumas Malone; Floyd House; budgets; minutes; Beardsley Ruml; space; program suggestions; organization plan; Social Science Research outlines for University of Chicago and Columbia University 1926 Jun-Dec (Box 12a)
- Institute for Research in the Social Sciences (4 of 5)--Budgets; letters re Wylie Kilpatrick to become Associate Research Professor; annual reports; Douglas Southall Freeman, The News Leader, Richmond, Va. complimenting Gee; Beardsley Ruml for the Rockefeller Memorial; University of North Carolina report to Rockefeller Memorial; American Council of Learned Societies questionnaire on research; Institute Executive Council meeting 1927 (Box 12a)
- Institute for Research in the Social Sciences (5 of 5)-Edward L. Stone re Public and Private Welfare Survey of Roanoke, Va.; Gooch report to Gee on "Regionalism in France" study; Gee to Floyd H. Marvin, President, George Washington University re the Institute; Gee report re Va. Social Science Association; Alderman re Institute publications; Gee article for The Charlotte Observer, "Higher Education and Southern Progress"; minutes and report from Fall 1929 Institute meeting; annual report, 1927; Social Science Research Council Requests information; Rockefeller Memorial and Social Science Research Council re Gooch; Gee to Philip Parsons, University of Oregon, re Institute; 2nd Annual Report, 1928; Alderman to Ruml, Rockefeller Memorial, mentions lecture by Charles A. Beard at University of Virginia; Virginia Social Science Association re its own formation; Institute Brochure, 1927-1928; Institute Budget Sheet, 1928-1929 1928-1930 (Box 12a)
- Invitations to be represented (1-9 of 31) 1925-1930 (Box 13)
- Invitations to be represented (10-19 of 31) 1925-1930 (Box 14)
- Invitations to be represented (20-27 of 31) 1925-1930 (Box 15)
- Invitations to be represented (28-31 of 31) 1925-1930 (Box 16)
- "J" Miscellaneous--Jackson, Ed, governor of Indiana; Jaffe, Louis I.; Consulate General of Japan; Jarman, J.L., president of State Teacher's College, Farmville [Longwood]; Jefferson, Thomas; Jefferson Society 1925-1930 (Box 16)
- Jefferson Memorial Foundation 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 16)
- "K" Miscellaneous --Kahn Foundation for Foreign Travel, James Southall Wilson proposed; Kallenbach scholarship; Kappa Delta Pi; Fiske Kimball 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 17)
- "L" Miscellaneous --La Baume, F. re cigarette smoking; laboratory courses; letters to W.W. Laird re idea of approaching Du Pont family to set up school of Social Sciences; Lake Placid Club; Lancaster, Dabney S.; Lane company re offer to sell property; Lee, Lawrence; R. E. Lee Memorial Foundation; Lefevre portrait; Lewis, Ivey re University Bibliography; Lincoln Scholarship Fund; Loan Fund 1925-1930, (3 folders) (Box 17)
- Latin 1925-1930 (Box 17)
- Law Department, General--letter to John Bassett Moore re strengthening instruction in International Law; recent Law Library acquisitions; needs of the Law School 1925-1930 (Box 17)
- Law Department Teaching Staff 1925-1930 (Box 17)
- League of Nations Non-Partisan Association--Alderman to serve on National Advisory Council 1925-1930 (Box 17)
- Lectures, see also Barbour-Page lectures 1925-1930 (Box 17)
- Lecturer Baccalaureate 1925-1930 (Box 17)
- Legislative Bills re University of Virginia 1925-1930 (Box 17)
- Legislative Program --Report on progress of Agriculture in Virginia; budget; Byrd, Harry F. re the University; emphasis on medical program; Centennial celebration 1925-1930, (3 folders) (Box 18)
- Legislative Program newspaper clippings 1925-1930 (Box 18)
- Legislative Program statistics 1925-1930 (Box 18)
- Library, General --book lists; statistics; Poe portrait; James McConnell cap; fund for books on Negro [Arthur Curtiss James donation]; information re Jefferson manuscripts in library 1925-1930, (5 folders) (Box 18)
- Library, General --list of donors; Library Committee minutes 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 19)
- "M" Miscellaneous --McConnell statue; Maphis, Charles G.; Memminger, C. G. re Baron Powell Rammingen's autograph collection; Metcalf, J. C. re books on Negroes for the library [Arthur Curtiss James donation] 1925-1930, (7 folders) (Box 19)
- McIntire Fund 1925-1930 (Box 19)
- Marshall Statue 1925-1930 (Box 19)
- Mathematics 1925-1930 (Box 19)
- Medicine, School of (1 of 2) 1925-1930 (Box 19)
- Medicine, School of (2 of 2) 1925-1930 (Box 20)
- Medicine, School of--Application for Superintendent 1925-1930 (Box 20)
- Medicine, School of--dedication 1925-1930 (Box 20)
- Medicine, School of--expansion 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 20)
- Medicine, School of--hospital 1925-1930 (Box 20)
- Medicine, School of--Hospital Superintendent's Reports 1925-1930 (Box 20)
- Medicine, School of--Hospital Ward Patient Statistics 1925-1930 (Box 20)
- Medicine, School of--Hough Memorial 1925-1930 (Box 21)
- Medicine, School of--Movement to raise $450,000 1925-1930, (3 folders) (Box 21)
- Medicine, School of--Nursing Chair 1925-1930 (Box 21)
- Medicine, School of--Pathology Department 1925-1930 (Box 21)
- Medicine, School of--Statistics 1925-1930 (Box 21)
- Medicine, School of--Teaching Staff 1925-1930 (Box 21)
- Medicine, School of--memorial to Walter Reed; Historical Sketch of Belroi 1925-1930 (Box 21)
- Miscellaneous--College shield; Alma Mater song; sabbatical leave; request for information about alumni and traditions at the University 1925-1930 (Box 21)
- "N" Miscellaneous (1 of 2)--Narcotics; National Committee for Mental Hygiene; National Education Association; National League of Women Voters 1925-1930 (Box 21)
- "N" Miscellaneous (2 of 2)--Near East College Association; Near East Relief 1925-1930 (Box 22)
- National Association of State Universities 1925-1930 (Box 22)
- "O" Miscellaneous--Omicron Delta Kappa 1925-1930 (Box 22)
- "P" Miscellaneous --Painting walls by students; Phelps-Stokes fellowships; Phi Kappa Sigma Fraternity; Poe Room 1925-1930, (3 folders) (Box 22)
- Page School of International Relations at Johns Hopkins 1925-1930 (Box 22)
- Pan American Celebration: Bolivar mementoes 1925-1930 (Box 22)
- Peace Pamphlets and Letters 1925-1930 (Box 22)
- Phi Beta Kappa 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 22)
- Philosophy--suggestions for enrichment and enlargement of graduate work in philosophy; portrait of Albert Lefevre; proposed changes in the course "History of Philosophy" 1925-1930 (Box 23)
- Physical Education 1925-1930 (Box 23)
- Physics 1925-1930 (Box 23)
- Political Science--Geneva School on International Studies 1925-1930 (Box 23)
- Prohibition 1925-1930 (Box 23)
- Prospective Donors 1925-1930 (Box 23)
- Psychology--W and L Record Card 1925-1930 (Box 23)
- Public Health and Hygiene 1925-1930 (Box 23)
- Public Speaking 1925-1930 (Box 23)
- "Q" Miscellaneous--Quarles, Fred, president of Omicron Delta Kappa; Queen of Rumania 1925-1930 (Box 23)
- Questionnaires 1925-1930 (Box 23)
- "R" Miscellaneous --Randolph, Hollings, list of graduates of law Class, 1895; Raskob, John J.; Rockefeller, Jr., J. D.; Rural Sociology 1925-1930, (4 folders) (Box 23)
- Radio --Report on radio broadcasting; Alderman's acceptance as member of Advisory Council to National Broadcasting Company; Stringfellow Barr's ideas; hearings before the United States Senate; George Zehmer suggestions 1925-1930, (3 folders) (Box 24)
- Radio Broadcasting Systems at High Schools and Universities 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 24)
- Recommendations, Letters of 1925-1930 (Box 24)
- Religious Exercises 1925-1930 (Box 24)
- Research--Proposed establishment of an institution for research in the Social Sciences 1925-1930 (Box 25)
- Rhodes Scholarship 1925-1930 (Box 25)
- Rockefeller Commission: Appeal for grant for library for cataloging 1925-1930 (Box 25)
- Romance Languages--Bolivar; plan to furnish Romance Pavilion with antiques; Ormond Smith gift to french Room; Claude Swanson re dedication of French Room 1925-1930 (Box 25)
- "S" Miscellaneous --Scott, Frederic; seal; Self help student employment; University Senate re Yellow Journal; Seven Society re Jim McConnell; making of Shenandoah National Park; Sigma Xi; Silver, W.H. re iron spike from Rotunda, 1895 fire presented to University of Virginia; Social Sciences Institute; student fees; student health; student organizations 1925-1930, (8 folders) (Box 25)
- "S" Miscellaneous--Swannanoa; Swanson, Claude; death of Symmers student 1925-1930 (Box 26)
- Salary Increases 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 26)
- Sesquicentennial--plaster model of University of Virginia by Victor Mindeleff 1925-1930 (Box 26)
- Smith Campaign --F. D. Roosevelt letter 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 26)
- Sociology--tentative six-year program for the development of the School of Sociology 1925-1930 (Box 26)
- Southern Women's Educational Alliance Fellowship in Sociology 1925-1930 (Box 26)
- Statistics 1925-1930 (Box 26)
- Sullivan Foundation Award--given by N.Y. Southern Society--bronze plague for "admirable spiritual qualities" 1925-1930 (Box 27)
- Summer Session 1925-1930 (Box 27)
- Summer Work 1925-1930 (Box 27)
- "T" Miscellaneous -- College Topics; Tunstall, Robert B., re Dartmouth 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 27)
- Term Reports--statistics of number of enrollments in each class, number dropped, number passing and failing 1925-1930 (Box 27)
- "U" Miscellaneous--Underwood, Oscar W., editorial at time of his death; United Daughters of the Confederacy; U. S. departments; University Club of New York; University Cruising Club 1925-1930 (Box 27)
- University Hour--budgets; schedule 1925-1930 (Box 27)
- University Houses: Applications for the Pavilions 1925-1930 (Box 27)
- "V" Miscellaneous--Van Demark, R. W., renomination of Samuel Colcord for Nobel Peace Prize 1925-1930 (Box 27)
- "V" Miscellaneous--Varsity Club; Veterans' Bureau; Virginia Academy of Science 1925-1930 (Box 28)
- Virginia Constitution--revision of 1925-1930 (Box 28)
- Virginia Quarterly Review 1925-1930 (Box 28)
- Visitors, Board of-- 1925-1930, (3 folders) (Box 28)
- Visitors, Board of--Members 1925-1930 (Box 28)
- "W" Miscellaneous 1925-1930, (2 folders) (Box 29)
- William H. White Foundation 1925-1930 (Box 29)
- Women at the University 1925-1930 (Box 29)
- Woodrow Wilson Film 1925-1930 (Box 29)
- Woodrow Wilson Foundation 1925-1930 (Box 29)
- Woodrow Wilson Memorial Tablet 1925-1930 (Box 29)
- "X-Y" Miscellaneous--Yale; Yellow Journal--see Senate 1925-1930 (Box 29)